today we're going to be looking at how
you can actually calculate a spread call
option on two indices we're going to be
looking at the nasdaq and the s p 500.
now we've actually done a previous video
on this where we computed the call value
of the spread however we are now going
to incorporate stochastic volatility
into our models so in previous videos
we've recently been looking at the
heston model which uses the square root
variance process to get a stochastic
volatility measure while computing
option prices we're now going to apply
this to our spread call option of these
two indices so without further ado let's
get into it so let's go through this
jupiter notebook so one of the many
benefits of the monte carlo simulation
process is that we can actually price
under different multiple factors so i
refer to multiple underlyings of asset
prices of stochastic volatility and even
changes in interest rates so in this
tutorial we're going to be exploring the
pricing of a european spread call option
on the difference between two stock
indices here we'll be considering the
nasdaq and the s p 500
now we're going to be looking at a more
general stochastic process so the sdes
will have stochastic volatility as
described by the heston model that was
developed in 1993. so our spread call
option comes down to a few sds so under
the heston model we have two sdes for
the underlying asset price and two sdes
for the variance process for the stock
asset prices under risk neutral measures
we have our deterministic component
which takes in the risk-free rate and
then our
discrete distributions so this is the
dividend distributions and then we have
our diffusion component which is
dependent on this square root of
variance process so the volatility is
modeled by the square root variance
process so variance is modeled as a mean
reversion process so here we've got
kappa which symbolizes the rate of mean
reversion we've got theta which is the
long run mean of this variance process
we've got v1 which we're directly
modeling and we've got our sigma which
is like the volatility of the variance
process so the volatility of volatility
essentially
now you'll notice here that we have
four different winer processors that
we're trying to model at the same time
so the monte carlo procedure is exactly
the same as for a normal spread call
option which we've done a video one
before for the nasdaq and s p 500
except here we have a more complicated
correlation matrix between these whiner
processes
so we have to simulate these four at the
same time
here we have a special correlation
matrix which describes the relationship
between each one of these winer
processes so we have the relationship
between
the nasdaq and then the s p 500 variance
process so the linear relationships
between each one of these winer
processes is described in this
correlation matrix
now the notation as we went through
we've got st is the financial index so
we've got
the variance is vt c is going to be the
european call option price k for the
strike price which is actually going to
be specified as a difference between
the indices in terms of points we've got
uh weiner process w we've got the
interest rate the discrete dividend
payment
we've spoken about kappa theta and then
we also need this
v for the initial variance we've got
sigma is the volatility of variance and
then our row is the correlation
parameter we've got t which is the
current date and we've got t which is
the maturity date so a while back we
actually discussed how we could use
futures eruptions so we could speculate
on a divergence between the spread of
the s p
and the nasdaq indices we're going to
follow through with this example but now
we're going to be incorporating
stochastic volatility under the heston
model
so we're going to use the same
parameters that we had back on the 1st
of march 2022 so you're just going to
copy this from my website
and we're going to import some
dependencies so we've got numpy time and
from scipy linear algebra module we're
going to take koleski this is for the
cholesky decomposition of that
correlation matrix
so here we've got some heston specific
model parameters and i've just made
these up for this example so if you want
to know how you can actually calibrate
the hester model and find out what the
best parameters to use for your option
prices you can we've actually done a
complete video on this step where we
used the market option prices and then
calibrated the hester model to find the
best fit using mse so we've got theta
kappa and sigma
defined for both of our assets and we
have the initial variances of both
processes
then we've defined our correlation
matrix between the winer process under
the risk neutral measure so again you
can find all this in a video that we've
done before so now for the slow
implementation let's take a
slower look at how we're actually going
to compute this monte carlo simulation
and we'll do this for each time step for
each simulation
so here we're going to define the monte
carlo specific parameters so here we've
got a thousand discrete time steps and
we've got a thousand number of
simulations so we're just going to start
the timer because we want to see how
long it actually takes
let's pre-compute the constants our time
step each time is just going to be our
total t one year divided by n
and then our lognormal prices are just
going to be numpy log of the nasdaq for
our first asset price and then our
second is going to be the s p 500
so for the hester model adjustments for
each time step we're going to take the
kappa that we've defined over that
yearly period and we're going to place
that in terms of our time steps so let's
adjust the kappa
the rate of mean reversion uh just by a
straight dt and then for our sigma the
volatility of variance process we're
just going to take the square root of dt
and multiply that to our sigma
and of course our variance process we're
just going to make sure that that's
initialized with our original variances
for each asset
now
performing lower colossal decomposition
essentially what we're doing here we're
finding the lower triangle of our
correlation matrix and we're going to be
using this to multiply through
by random normal variables to get our
correlated whiner variables
so the standard error places
placeholders this is just going to be
used to actually complete the error that
around our calculation so running
through our monte carlo simulation here
we've got for each simulation i and m we
have our log prices initialized then
we're going to step through time so for
each time step j we need to generate the
correlated whiner variables so i'm going
to do this by actually simulating
standard normal distributed variables
four of them so with a mean of zero and
a standard deviation of one and then
we're going to compute the inner product
so do matrix multiplication of this z
correlated
of these z uncorrelated variables and
multiply them through by our lower
cholesky decomposition of our
correlation matrix then we're going to
get
the whiner
array which is just our correlated
variables
we can then take our simulated variance
processes and we need to do this first
so here we have
variance which is equal to the initial
variance plus our mean reversion rate
multiplied by
theta which is that long term variance
minus our current variance plus our
volatility of variance times by the
square root of the variance at the
current time step we then multiply this
diffusion component by our whiner
process and you need to make sure that
you use the correct index for your
specific term so here um we actually
looked at things in terms of asset price
one asset price two variance one
variance two so i need to index on the
respective indices for the thing that
i'm trying to calculate
we do the same thing for variance
process 2 and now that we have those we
can then use that to calculate our log
asset prices so first the deterministic
components we've got the risk-free rate
minus the dividend minus 0.5 times by
the variance and that's all multiplied
by the time step
we then use that to compute our log
asset price in the next time step so we
use the log asset price of the time step
before plus our deterministic component
plus our diffusion component which is
just going to be the square root of the
variance times by our time step we then
multiply that all through by our whiner
process of this specific correlated
variable
then after we run through all the time
periods to time t then we get the last
asset price log asset price and we take
the exponential to get the correct asset
price and this is in terms of the index
so this will be in points so if then for
the call option we take the max between
the difference between asset 1 and asset
2 index price and then we minus k which
we just described as the strike which
was the difference at the time that we
started of the difference between the
indexes so then we complete this process
for m number of simulations so i think
we had i in m number of simulations and
then we can compute the expectation and
then the standard error so for the
expectation we end up getting 830 bucks
with a standard error of 46 dollars now
it's important to know that calculation
time here has taken
16.43 seconds now for the fast
implementation what we're going to do is
we're going to vectorize this option
pricing so now i'm using the same
discrete time steps and the number of
simulations now the only difference is
i'm getting this generated correlated
wider variables and i'm doing this
outside of our for loop so now we've got
these random normal variables of size n
by m by four so this is our time steps
by the number of simulations by our four
variables for each one of those
conditions
we then can compute our correlated um
vet one of variables for each time step
for each simulation by just multiplying
computing the inner product between zed
our random normal variables and our
lower colossky decomposition
we then need arrays for storing our
prices in our variances and i'm going to
use shape n plus 1 so i can store the
first price and then the first variance
i'm then going to fill these values with
the log of asset price 1 and asset price
2 and then our initial variances
now stepping through this process all we
need to do now for the monte carlo
simulation is run through time we're
gonna run through time from one through
to n plus one
so simulating the variance process we
just used the same formula as before but
now we're indexing on the previous time
period and we're saving it into the
current time period
we then also need to remember to
correctly index our whiner process so we
have our
n which is our time so we index by time
we take all of our
simulated
variables so all of our m simulations
and then we need to index the correct uh
whiner process for the respective asset
that we we're calculating at the time
we can then calculate our log asset
prices by getting the drift terms first
and then indexing on the current time
that we've just calculated and then we
can get our at log asset prices by using
the previous log asset price plus the
current
drift term and then our current
diffusion term which is going to be our
current variance
multiplied by time step taken to the
square root multiplied by the respective
whiner process
the reason i'm indexing from before is
because i only created a matrix
of n by m in length
we then take the exponential of our log
prices and then we use the final asset
prices to compute our call price
so then we can see that we get a call
value of 895 here with a similar
standard error as before but the
calculation time has taken 0.25 seconds
that's a 60 time improvement in terms of
computation time so now visualization
i'm just going to show you we can get
the index spread options now with
stochastic volatility and you can see
the relative
simulations i've only shown four here
but obviously we did a thousand for
between the nasdaq and the s p with
changing variances if you enjoyed the
video please give it a thumbs up and
subscribe if you're not already to the
channel if you'd like to get more
involved with the
community that we're trying to build
here and be involved with like-minded
individuals you should go ahead and look
at the patreon link in the description
below